Since 2003, a special type of scam targeting the elderly
Od roku 2003 w Japonii króluje biorące na cel osoby starsze
called the money transfer scam has proliferated in Japan.
oszustwo zwane „przekrętem na przelew”.
Financial damages increased every year, reaching 56.5 billion yen in 2014.
Straty finansowe rosną z roku na rok. W 2014 r. wynosiły 56,5 miliarda jenów.
Now, in 2019, scammers have changed their techniques,
W 2019 roku oszuści zmienili metody,
and the damage continues.
w dalszym ciągu okradając obywateli.
APRIL 2009
KWIECIEŃ 2009 R.
TOKYO SECOND OFFICE OPERATING REVENUES
DRUGIE BIURO W TOKIO PRZYCHODY OPERACYJNE
Where did we leave off yesterday?
Na czym wczoraj skończyliśmy?
I think we were on number 80.
Jakoś na numerze 80.
Let's go with this one.
Zacznijmy od tego.
Let's do this!
Do dzieła!
Hello.
Halo?
Mom! It's me, Kensuke!
Mamo, to ja, Kensuke!
I'm sorry... I'm so sorry...
Tak mi przykro...
-Hey, hand over the phone! -Kensuke? What's going on?
- Dawaj telefon! - Kensuke? Co się dzieje?
What's happening?
Co się stało?
Hey, old lady! What kind of piece of trash son did you raise?
Posłuchaj, jędzo! Wychowałaś kawał gnoja!
He put his hands on my daughter! He's through!
Obłapiał moją córkę! Już po nim!
I'll tell the entire world.
Powiem o tym całemu światu,
I'll send letters to his company, his clients, everywhere!
powiadomię jego firmę, klientów, każdego!
-Don't test me, got it? -Sorry...
- Ze mną się nie zadziera! - Przepraszam...
-Please, wait! -Hello, is this Kensuke's mother?
- Chwileczkę! - Czy rozmawiam z matką Kensukego?
-Yes! -This is Sugiyama with the station police.
- Tak! - Mówi Sugiyama z policji.
Around eight a.m., your son was arrested for groping a woman on the train,
Około ósmej pani syna aresztowano za obmacywanie kobiety w pociągu.
and we're currently investigating him.
Obecnie jest przesłuchiwany.
-You bastard! -I'm sorry!
- Ty draniu! - Przepraszam!
Stop that right now! Please, calm down!
Proszę się uspokoić!
-The victim's father is very upset. -Please...
- Ojciec ofiary jest wściekły. - Błagam...
Normally, we would take him to the police station
Zwykle trafiłby na komisariat
and have him wait in jail until his trial, but seeing as he's admitted his guilt...
i zaczekał na proces w areszcie, ale jako że przyznał się do winy...
If possible, we'd like to settle this out of court.
Możemy załatwić sprawę polubownie.
-Mommy! -Settle?
- Mamo! - Polubownie?
If it's okay, I'll send someone to your house now,
Mogę wysłać do pani kogoś
and they can pick up the agreed-upon settlement fee.
po odbiór wyznaczonej kwoty zadośćuczynienia.
If you agree, this becomes a civil case, and the police won't need to get involved.
Zostanie jedynie postępowanie cywilne, bez udziału policji.
-Yes, please! -Thank you very much.
- Zgadzam się! - Dziękuję.
-We got her! -Yes!
- Jest nasza! - Tak!
This is a classic three-person scam called the "station cop."
Ten trzyosobowy numer nazwano „na gliniarza”.
Basically, one person pretends to be a train station police officer.
Jedna z osób udaje policjanta.
Every day, I scam the elderly out of their money.
Każdego dnia wyciskam oszczędności ze starszych osób.
And I don't lose a wink of sleep over it.
Wcale nie spędza mi to snu z powiek.
BANK ATM BANK - CREDIT UNION - ONLINE BANKING
BANKOMAT BANK - KASA KREDYTOWA - BANK ONLINE
WARNING!! SCAM ALERT SECURITY CAMERAS IN USE
UWAGA NA OSZUSTÓW OBIEKT MONITOROWANY
EPISODE 1
ODCINEK 1
PLEASE SELECT A TRANSACTION
WYBIERZ RODZAJ TRANSAKCJI
WITHDRAWAL
WYPŁATA ŚRODKÓW
PLEASE ENTER YOUR PIN NUMBER
WPROWADŹ PIN
This card cannot be used.
Nie można użyć tej karty.
What do I do now?
Co teraz?
I have no more money.
Nie mam już kasy.
-Can you spot me? -No way!
- Pomożesz mi? - Bez jaj!
-Please! -No way. It's called self-reliance.
- Daj spokój! - To się nazywa samodzielność.
-No one will save you. -How can you say that to a friend?
- Nikt ci nie pomoże. - Jak możesz tak mówić przyjacielowi?
You crack me up!
Rozśmieszasz mnie.
You thought you were hot stuff when you first graduated.
Po szkole myślałeś, że jesteś kimś.
-Stop it! -University is the biggest scam out there.
- Przestań. - Studia to największa ściema.
With tuition and living costs, it's over ten million yen a year for four years.
Czesne i koszty życia to rocznie dziesięć milionów, przez cztery lata.
How are you supposed to pay that off?
Skąd na to wziąć?
You're full of excuses.
Ciągle masz wymówki.
The world is harsh, and it's cold.
Świat jest okrutny.
Even people who are able to get a job, end up getting fired. Like you.
Nawet ci, którzy mogą znaleźć pracę,
-Welcome! -I'm sorry, I'm late!
- Dzień dobry! - Przepraszam za spóźnienie!
-Misaki, you're going to love this. -Love what?
- Spodoba ci się to, Misaki. - Co?
-Pay for me. -Idiot.
- Zapłać za mnie. - Kretyn.
-Excuse me, one beer please! -Right away!
- Poproszę piwo. - Robi się.
If you really need the money, I know of a good part-time gig.
Jeśli tak potrzebujesz forsy, to mam dla ciebie fuchę.
How much?
Ile?
About 300,000 yen for two or three hours.
Trzysta tysięcy za dwie, może trzy godziny.
-Really? That exists? -I know a guy that gets around.
- Tak można? - Znam jednego gościa.
That's super sketchy.
Podejrzana sprawa.
Trust me, it's a legit part-time job!
Zaufaj mi, legalny biznes.
You could say it's a finance job.
W finansach, można rzec.
That's even more suspicious.
To coraz bardziej śmierdzi.
You'll make a killing!
Zarobisz fortunę!
It's better than working at some no-name place. Besides--
Lepsze to niż praca w jakiejś nieznanej dziurze. Poza tym...
-Sorry... Wow, you're cute! -Boss!
- Sorry... Ale śliczna buźka! - Szefie!
-Sorry. -Hey, you, drink.
- Przepraszam. - Pij.
-I said drink! Chug it! -Right away!
- Pij, mówię! Do dna! - Tak jest!
-You drink, too! -Jeez...
- Ty też! - Rany.
Look at them, coming to a cheap pub with their boss
Spójrzcie tylko. Idą z szefem do taniej knajpy
and chugging drinks to try and get on his good side...
i chleją, chcąc mu się przypodobać.
Makoto, let's do it.
Śmiało, Makoto.
No, thanks.
Nie, dzięki.
You wimp! This is why you're single.
Mięczak. Dlatego jesteś sam.
What? You two aren't dating?
Nie jesteście parą?
That's 1,000% impossible.
Nawet za milion lat.
"1,000%"? That's a lot.
Milion? To dużo.
-It's been growing since we were kids. -Here you are!
- Znamy się od dziecka. - Piwko!
Cheers!
Zdrowie!
So you're single, Makoto?
Jesteś singlem, Makoto?
-Come to me! -No way!
- Zapraszam! - No nie!
-You're the worst. -It's my mom.
- Baran. - To moja mama.
Hey, Mom. I'm eating with Misaki and the others, so I don't need dinner.
Cześć. Jem kolację z Misaki i resztą, nie będę głodny.
Hey, calm down.
Spokojnie.
What?
Co?
What about Dad?
Tata?
What's wrong?
Co się stało?
What did you say?
Co pan mówi?
Your father has developed cancer in his eye.
Twój ojciec ma nowotwór oka.
It's quite advanced,
Dość rozwinięty,
so we'll either have to remove it or look into terminal care.
więc trzeba usunąć oko lub szukać opieki terminalnej.
Does that mean he'll die if we don't remove his eye?
Umrze, jeśli nie wytniecie oka?
Yes.
Tak.
Also, even if we perform the surgery to remove the cancer,
A nawet jeśli przeprowadzimy zabieg,
he may not be completely cured.
nie musi to oznaczać, że zostanie wyleczony.
The cancer may metastasize.
Mogą wystąpić przerzuty.
Is there really no other way?
Nie ma innego rozwiązania?
There is a new, cutting-edge treatment.
Istnieje pewna eksperymentalna metoda.
It does not damage the eye, and some patients have fully recovered.
Nie powoduje uszkodzenia oka, kilku pacjentów dzięki niej wyzdrowiało.
However, it is not covered by insurance.
Jednak
Not covered by insurance?
Nie obejmuje?
That means it's really expensive, right?
Czyli jest bardzo droga?
-That's right. -Is there anything we can do?
- Zgadza się. - Możemy coś zrobić?
Those are the rules.
Takie są zasady.
Then why do we even pay our taxes?
Po co w takim razie płacimy podatki?
Why does insurance cover some diseases and not others?
Dlaczego ubezpieczenie obejmuje tylko niektóre choroby?
We pay taxes because we want to be taken care of.
Płacimy podatki, żeby ktoś się nami zajął.
Those are the rules, so there's nothing I can do about it.
Takie są zasady. Nie mam na nie wpływu.
"The world is harsh"?
„Świat jest okrutny”?
"No one will save you"?
„Nikt ci nie pomoże”?
This isn't some kind of joke!
To nie jest żart!
Some things happen suddenly.
Czasem życie nas zaskakuje.
This came for you.
To do ciebie.
It's a payment reminder for your student loans.
Przypomnienie o spłacie kredytu studenckiego.
As if we don't have enough problems.
Jakby mało nam było problemów.
Seeing this just makes me more anxious.
Tylko bardziej się przez to denerwuję.
I'm sorry.
Przepraszam.
Hey, don't apologize.
Nie przepraszaj.
I'm not a kid anymore. I'll figure something out.
Nie jestem dzieckiem, coś wymyślę.
I have an interview at a big company tomorrow.
Jutro idę na rozmowę w wielkiej firmie.
I'll get a job, and I'll work day and night.
Dostanę pracę
Things will turn out okay.
Wszystko będzie dobrze.
Makoto Kusano, graduated from Churitsu University.
Makoto Kusano, uniwersytet Churitsu.
Worked at Mitsuura Real Estate...
Praca w firmie Mitsuura...
That's a big company. What did you do there?
To spora firma. Co pan tam robił?
Yes, I worked with corporate clients.
Obsługiwałem klientów biznesowych.
Why did you quit after six months?
Dlaczego tylko pół roku?
-The company was offering buyouts, so-- -I see.
- Zaproponowali wypłatę należności... - Rozumiem.
So you were fired during the recession.
Zwolniono pana w wyniku recesji.
No, I wasn't. I could have stayed, but...
Nie. Mogłem zostać, ale...
I wasn't comfortable with a company that would ask that of a new hire.
Nie chciałem zostać w firmie, która proponuje to nowym pracownikom.
So you chose to leave.
Postanowił pan odejść.
Yes.
Tak.
Things are tough here. Starting salaries are 140,000 yen.
U nas nie jest lekko. Na początku płacimy 140 tysięcy.
Or maybe it was 120,000. I forgot.
Albo 120, nie pamiętam.
Everyone works late, and no one has time to teach others how to do things.
Wszyscy pracują do późna, nie ma czasu na przyuczanie nowych.
So you'd really just have to learn on the job.
Będzie pan się uczyć w praktyce.
I can do it. I'll be okay.
Poradzę sobie.
-Okay? -I mean...
- Na pewno? - W sensie...
The number one reason I applied for a job here is--
Chcę dostać tę pracę, ponieważ...
Nakano!
Nakano!
I'm sorry. I can't figure out Excel. Could you show me how to do it?
Nie ogarniam tego Excela. Pomożesz mi?
Excel? Oh, you mean the thing I asked for this morning?
Excela? Do arkusza, o który prosiłem rano?
I'll take care of it myself later.
Sam się później nim zajmę.
-Really? -Yes.
- Naprawdę? - Tak.
-Okay then. -Thank you.
- No dobrze. - Dziękuję.
Sorry.
Przepraszam.
We're done here.
Skończyliśmy.
-What? -Yeah.
- To koniec? - Tak.
-Hey.
- Cześć.
-Where's Sachiko? -Mom is resting right now.
- Gdzie Sachiko? - Mama odpoczywa.
-I see. -Yeah.
Rozumiem.
My mom is worried.
Moja mama się martwi.
We're nearby, so let us know if you need anything.
Daj znać, gdybyście czegoś potrzebowali.
Okay.
Jasne.
-Do you have work today? -Yeah.
- Pracujesz dziś? - Tak.
Are you going somewhere?
Idziesz gdzieś?
I was going to go shopping.
Chciałem iść na zakupy.
-Towards the station? Let's go together. -No, don't worry about it.
- W stronę stacji? Pójdę z tobą. - Nie trzeba.
See you later.
Do zobaczenia.
We're going to make a killing.
Zbijemy fortunę.
-Shotaro... -What?
- Shotaro... - No?
Thanks.
Dzięki.
We're friends, right? We have to help each other.
Przyjaźnimy się, nie? Musimy sobie pomagać.
Behind you...
Za tobą.
How are you?
Co tam?
I just got back from an erotic massage, so I'm feeling great!
Wracam z masażu erotycznego, jest super.
Good to hear.
To świetnie.
There are three convenience stores and two small branch offices.
Mamy tu trzy spożywczaki i dwa mniejsze biura.
There's tons of ATMs and not many people.
Masa bankomatów i niewiele osób.
Awesome!
Super!
-I'm going to make a phone call. -Got it.
- Muszę zadzwonić. - Jasne.
-Here. -Thanks.
- Trzymaj. - Dzięki.
-And for Makoto. -Thanks...
- I dla Makota.
Hey, put some on.
Masz, nałóż.
What's that?
Co to?
It keeps your fingerprints off the ATMs.
Nie zostawisz odcisków na bankomatach.
That's right, we're doing the money transfer scam.
Robimy przekręt na przelew.
-Did you just figure it out? -Screw you.
- Nie domyśliłeś się? - Wal się.
Hold on. You'll be in trouble if you leave now.
Wysiądź, a będziesz miał kłopoty.
This is a serious crime.
To poważna sprawa.
If you back out, Yamada will kill you.
Jeśli się wycofasz, Yamada cię zabije.
He'll really do it. I'm telling you, he's dangerous.
Poważnie. To niebezpieczny facet.
So what?
Co z tego?
Calm down! Calm down and listen.
Uspokój się i posłuchaj.
All we have to do is follow orders and withdraw the money.
Musimy tylko wykonać polecenia i wypłacić forsę.
The real criminals are the people at the top.
Prawdziwe bandziory siedzą nad nami.
We won't get caught, I promise.
Nikt nas nie złapie. Obiecuję.
We get 10% of the money we take out. For two million yen, we get 200,000.
Dostaniemy dziesięć procent prowizji. Dwieście tysięcy z dwóch milionów.
For ten million, we get one million.
Milion z dziesięciu.
A job will pay you only 100,000 a month for being young and then bleed you dry.
W robocie dostaniesz sto koła miesięcznie, a urobisz się po łokcie.
How long will it take to save money? Never mind saving, you can't even survive!
Ile czasu będziesz odkładał? Ba, nawet się za to nie utrzymasz.
If no one will help you, then you have to help yourself.
Skoro nikt ci nie pomoże, musisz sam sobie pomóc!
That's how it is, even if you have to take risks!
Tak już jest. Trzeba zaryzykować.
Welcome.
Witamy.
The PIN is incorrect.
Nieprawidłowy PIN.
You! That's clever.
No nie! Ale spryciarz!
Recently, banks are always bothering you about changing your PIN.
Ostatnio ciągle każą zmienić PIN.
As if changing it does anything!
Jakby to miało coś dać!
I can never remember my number, so I'm always having problems.
Ja nigdy go nie pamiętam,
WARNING!! SCAM ALERT
UWAGA NA OSZUSTÓW
SCAMS ON THE RISE
CORAZ WIĘCEJ OSZUSTÓW
POLICE ON DUTY
POLICJA CZUWA
Money transfer scam?
Przekręt na przelew?
Hey!
Hej!
Stop right there!
Nie ruszaj się!
Hey, stop! Get him!
Stój! Brać go!
It's Shotaro! Shotaro's in trouble!
Shotaro ma kłopoty!
Get in, idiot! Hurry up!
Wsiadaj, idioto! Szybko!
Hey!
Ej!
Hold on! Wait!
Stój! Zaczekaj!
I said wait!
Poczekaj!
-Leave me alone! -Stop running!
- Zostawcie mnie! - Zatrzymaj się!
-Go away! -Wait! Stop!
- Precz! - Czekaj!
Hey!
Czekaj!
Get in!
Wsiadaj!
Stop!
Stój!
Stop where you are!
Nie ruszaj się!
-Stop the car! -Shut up!
- Zatrzymać wóz! - Morda!
Hurry it up!
Szybciej!
-We're losing them! We're getting away! -Oh, no!
- Zaraz ich zgubimy! - O nie!
Wait!
Czekajcie!
-Look at this! -Stop!
- Patrz! - Przestań!
I understand the situation.
Rozumiem.
It's fine as long as they weren't arrested.
Najważniejsze, żeby ich nie aresztowano.
But the one sounds like he could be interesting.
Ale tamten może się przydać.
Hey, idiot, look over here!
Spójrz tutaj, jełopie!
Look at his legs!
Patrz na jego nogi!
He's really scared!
Jaki przerażony!
Look at his legs move!
Ale się wierci!
You better stop moving!
Przestań się tak rzucać!
Good morning!
Dzień dobry!
You're in real trouble now, asshole!
Teraz masz przerąbane, śmieciu!
What's going on?
Co się stało?
Your friend ran off with my money.
Twój koleś zwiał z forsą.
Can you believe that?
Uwierzysz?
The kids who we get to withdraw the money are always spineless bastards.
Zawsze na takie fuchy trafiają się gówniarze pozbawieni godności.
I'm sorry!
Przykro mi!
Hey!
Koleś!
I heard your poor daddy is in the hospital.
Ponoć twój tatuś leży w szpitalu.
Shall I string him up next to you?
Podwiesić go obok ciebie?
That would help get his blood flowing!
Poprawiłoby mu to krążenie.
Stop, please! Please don't...
Przestańcie, proszę!
Please, just leave my family alone!
Zostawcie moją rodzinę.
I'll do anything! I'll do anything you want!
Zrobię wszystko, co chcecie!
There it is! "I'll do anything!"
No proszę, wszystko!
Damn straight you will.
Zgadza się, zrobisz.
There are some fellas who have taken an interest in you.
Paru gości się tobą interesuje.
They want a lively idiot of their own.
Szukają narwanego kretyna.
Question time!
A teraz zagadki!
What line of work are they in?
Czym się zajmują?
I don't know!
Nie wiem!
-Use your head for a second! -This isn't some kind of game!
- Użyj mózgu! - To nie jest zabawa!
Hey, punk!
Pajacu!
I'll give you the answer.
Powiem ci.
They're in the scamming business as well. But they're not looking for a lackey.
Też siedzą w przekrętach. Ale nie szukają pomagiera.
You'll be scamming old people over the phone.
Będziesz ściemniał dziadków przez telefon.
Time for you to see some real action!
Czas na prawdziwą zabawę!
Hey.
Pamiętaj.
Don't be late, got it?
Nie spóźnij się.
If you run, you're dead.
Zwiej i nie żyjesz.
There has been an increasing number of money transfer scams,
Ostatnio coraz częściej dochodzi do prób wyłudzenia przelewów.
so please be wary of unsolicited calls.
Należy uważać na niespodziewane telefony.
BEWARE OF SCAMS!
UWAGA NA OSZUSTÓW!
I made it! Did I make it?
Zdążyłem! Tak?
I made it, right?
Zdążyłem?
You're ten seconds late!
Dziesięć sekund spóźnienia.
If you're late again tomorrow, we're taking one of your bones.
Powtórz to jutro, a stracisz kość.
I didn't hear you say hello.
Nie przywitaliście się.
Say hello!
Przywitać się!
-Hello... -Louder! Hello!
- Dzień dobry. - Głośniej! Dzień dobry!
-Hello!
- Dzień dobry!
You're all completely useless.
Jesteście bezużyteczni.
I'm Dokugawa, the one in charge here.
Nazywam się Dokugawa i to ja tu rządzę.
During this ten-day training, you all are going to witness hell.
Szkolenie trwa dziesięć dni. Urządzę wam piekło.